Guide to the Mary Freeman Crabbe Diaries
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Mary Freeman Crabbe diaries
1890-1895
SC0489
Crabbe, Mary Freeman.
0.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Tom Flood, 1995
Information about Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHY
Mary Freeman, from Woodland, California, attended Stanford University from 1893 to 1897, when she graduated with an a.b. in English. She lived in Roble Hall and, judging from the Stanford Quad, was not particularly active in student organizations. In 1908 she married John Hammond Crabbe.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
These diaries were recorded during two separate periods in Mary Freeman's life. There are three volumes written as a teenager from January 1, 1890 to December 31, 1891. Entries concern her daily activities such as school, visiting with friends, family matters, attending church, playing piano for church groups, and a summer visit to Nevada in 1891. These volumes also include various lists of parties attended, books read, and miscellaneous social events.
The second set of eight volumes was written between January 1, 1894 and December 31, 1895, during her second and third year at Stanford. These entries largely concern her social life as a student, with some mention of classes, exams, and study habits. She also mentions lectures attended, including those by David Starr Jordan, Benjamin Harrison, Harriet Hosmer, Helen Campbell, Walter Camp, and Susan B. Anthony. Other subjects of note include a "bachelor party" in Roble, a fraternity or club stunt at night outside Roble, a basketball game between Stanford women and the prep girls, a Halloween Dance at Roble Gym, and jokes among audiences before lectures began.
Access Terms
Anthony, Susan B., (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Camp, Walter Chauncey, 1859-1925; Campbell, Helen, 1839-1918.; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901; Hosmer, Harriet Goodhue, 1830-1908; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Students.;; College students.; Diaries.; Women.; Woodland (Calif.)--Social life and customs.
Collection Contents
- Diary, January 1, 1890 to December 31, 1890 (Folder 1)
- Diary, January 1, 1891 to August 31, 1891 (Folder 2)
- Diary, September 1, 1891 to December 31, 1891 (Folder 3)
- Diary, January 1, 1894 to March 25, 1894 (Folder 4)
- Diary, March 26, 1894 to June 10, 1894 (Folder 5)
- Diary, June 11, 1894 to August 6, 1894 (Folder 6)
- Diary, August 7, 1894 to October 6, 1894 (Folder 7)
- Diary, October 7, 1894 to February 6, 1895 (Folder 8)
- Diary, February 7, 1895 to Mary 6, 1895 (Folder 9)
- Diary, May 7, 1895 to August 22, 1895 (Folder 10)
- Diary, August 23, 1895 to December 31, 1895 (Folder 11)
PARTIAL INDEX TO VOLUME FOR JANUARY 1, 1894 TO MARCH 25, 1894
lecture by Joseph Le Conte page 20
talk by Jacob Voorsanger page 30
talk by David Starr Jordan page 32
lecture on Hull House by unnamed woman; comments on Stanford's lack of social life, in particular dancing page 54
"bachelor party" -women came dressed as men, smoked, drank "beer" (sarsaparilla), and imitated college men page 60-64
Frosh-Soph Tie-Up between classes of '96 and '97 page 66-68
talk by Harriet Hosmer and reception for her; mentions Professors Fairclough and Newcomer page 78-79
singing songs in the Quad and being chased out by the watchman page 98
comments on Benjamin Harris's visit to campus page 102-103
talk by John Joseph Keane; Mrs. Stanford was present page 103-104
a fraternity or club initiation stunt outside Roble Dorm page 104-106
Founders' Day service with Benjamin Harrison and Horace Davis page 107-108
basketball game between Stanford women and "prep" girls [probably Castilleja School] page 120-121
PARTIAL INDEX TO VOLUME FOR MARCH 26, 1894 TO JUNE 10, 1894
Stanford Glee Club concert in Woodland and reception at the Freeman home March 27
talk by Benjamin Harrison April 15
her friend Blanche votes for student body president (Mary is not in favor of woman suffrage) April 24
lecture by Helen Campbell on college woman May 8
David Starr Jordan visits Roble and reads poetry May 13
Memorial Exercises with talks by students May 15
PARTIAL INDEX TO VOLUME FOR AUGUST 7, 1894 TO OCTOBER 6, 1894
David Starr Jordan talk, mentions Stanford's financial troubles Sept. 25
PARTIAL INDEX TO VOLUME FOR OCTOBER 7, 1894 TO FEBRUARY 6, 1895
Reading by a Miss Calhoun; electric lights failed; jokes and songs in crowd while waiting for her to arrive -mentions Shirley Baker singing Oct. 9
Halloween party at Roble Gym, with visit of 50 ghosts (presumably male students) dancing on tennis courts and then trying to get into the gym Oct. 30
Lecture by Walter Camp on college athletics; reports on the jokes made prior to the talk Nov. 13
Football rally; band played music; boys danced but not the girls Nov. 23
PARTIAL INDEX TO VOLUME FOR FEBRUARY 7, 1895 TO MAY 6, 1895
Attended church services in new church in Palo Alto Mar. 10
Three lectures: Dr. Jordan on evolution; Jenkin Lloyd Jones on Emerson; Dr. Jordan on his trip to Mexico Mar. 19
PARTIAL INDEX TO VOLUME FOR MAY 7, 1895 TO AUGUST 23, 1895
Talk by Susan B. Anthony and Miss Shaw May 21
Faculty/Senior baseball game May 24
Graduation exercises May 29